Guide to the Bureau of Building Inspection, Department of Public Safety, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1877-1928 AIS.1971.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Bureau of Building Inspection, Department of Public Safety, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1877-1928, 1981-1992
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh (Pa.). Department of Public Safety
AIS.1971.10
69 Volumes (also on 7 reels of microfilm)
The Pittsburgh Department of Public Safety provides administrative, financial, and technical support for management of the Bureau of Building Inspection. This collection, arranged by ward, contains yearly dockets of building permits and monthly reports of issued building permits, including three volumes which span 1894-1908 of Allegheny City, Pennsylvania, prior to annexation by the City of Pittsburgh. This collection also contains a complaint (violation) docket; record books of new additions, alterations and repairs, and wiring permits. Digital reproductions of the microfilm are available online.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available online in the finding aid.
History
The Pittsburgh Department of Public Safety provides administrative, financial and technical support for management of the Bureau of Building Inspection (BBI) whose responsiblities include regulating the construction, demolition and occupancy of all buildings and structures within the City of Pittsburgh. The Bureau also reviews, approves and issues all permits required by code for the repair, alteration and/or addition to all public and private buildings and structures, as well as permits for new construction. The mission of BBI is to provide life safety and a better quality of living for the residents of Pittsburgh.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection, arranged by ward, contains yearly dockets of building permits and monthly reports of issued building permits, including three volumes which span 1894-1908 of Allegheny City, Pennsylvania, prior to annexation by the City of Pittsburgh. This collection also contains a complaint (violation) docket; record books of new additions, alterations and repairs, and wiring permits.
The collection does not include: Pittsburgh Bureau of Building Inspection, Building Permit Dockets - Volume 6, 1889.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by the Pittsburgh Bureau of Building Inspection on April 20, 1971.
Previous Citation
Bureau of Building Inspection, Department of Public Safety, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1877-1928, AIS.1971.10, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh, Department of Public Safety, Records, 1877-1928, ais 71:10, Archives of Industrial Society, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pa., 15260
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Government; Allegheny (Pa.) -- History
- Pittsburgh Bureau of Building Inspection, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains information regarding: Building Permit Dockets (1877-1916, 1981-1992), Monthly Reports - New Building and Addition Permits (1896-1928), Record Books of New Additions (1896-1916) and Alterations and Repairs (1897-1916) and Compliant (Violation) Dockets (1890-1898).
  Building Permit Dockets contain information on the date, owner, builder, building type under construction, additions and alterations, total number of buildings, number of stories, height, width, depth, value (cost), class of building and location.
  Monthly Reports - New Building and Addition Permits contain information on the month, permit type, total number of permits issued and value (cost) and a summary statement.
  Record Books of New Additions contain information on the date, owner, builder, addition type, value, building class, permit number and location.
  Record Books of Alterations and Repairs contain information on the date, permit number, owner name, contractor, cost and location.
  Compliant (Violation) Dockets contain information on the date, address, building type, cause of complaint, examination date, orders given, final dispositions and names of tenants, owners, complainants and arbitrators.
  - Building Permit Dockets, 1877-1916, 1981-1992; 1.
    - Volume 1, 1877-1881 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 1)
    - Volume 2, 1882-1883
    - Volume 3, 1884-1885
    - Volume 4, 1886-1887
    - Volume 5, 1888
    - Volume 6 (missing), 1889
    - Volume 7, 1890
    - Volume 8, 1891
    - Volume 9, 1892 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 2)
    - Volume 10, 1893
    - Volume 11, 1894
    - Volume 12, 1895
    - Volume 13, 1896
    - Volume 14, 1897
    - Volume 15, 1898
    - Volume 16, 1899
    - Volume 17, 1900
    - Volume 18, 1901
    - Volume 19, 1902
    - Volume 20, 1903
    - Volume 21, 1904-1905
    - Volume 22, 1905-1906 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 3)
    - Volume 23, 1906-1907
    - Volume 24, 1907-1908
    - Volume 25, 1909-1910
    - Volume 26, 1911
    - Volume 27, 1912
    - Volume 28, 1913
    - Volume 29, 1914-1915
    - Volume 30, 1916
    - Additions in 2013
    - Wards 1 thru 9, 19181-1992 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Volume 31)
    - Wards 10 thru 17, 1981-1992 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Volume 32)
    - Wards 18 thru 32, 1981-1992 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Volume 33)
  - Monthly Reports - New Building and Addition Permits, 1896-1928; 2.
    - Volume 1, February 1896- May 1909 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 3)
    - Volume 2, June 1909-December 1922 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 4)
    - Volume 3, 1923-1928
  - Record Books of New Additions, 1896-1916; 3.
    - Volume 1, 1896-1897 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 4)
    - Volume 2, 1898-1899
    - Volume 3, 1900-1901
    - Volume 4, 1902-1903
    - Volume 5, 1904-1905
    - Volume 6, 1905-1906
    - Volume 7, 1906-1908
    - Volume 8, 1909-1910
    - Volume 9, 1911
    - Volume 10, 1912
    - Volume 11, 1913
    - Volume 12, 1914-1915
    - Volume 13, 1916
  - Record Books of Alterations and Repairs, 1897-1916; 4.
    - Volume 1, 1897-1900 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 5)
    - Volume 2, 1901-1904
    - Volume 3, 1905-1909
    - Volume 4, 1909-1910
    - Volume 5, 1911-1912
    - Volume 6, 1912-1913
    - Volume 7, 1913-1914
    - Volume 8, 1914-1915
    - Volume 9, 1916
  - Compliant (Violation) Dockets, 1890-1898; 5.
    - Volume 1, 1890-1896 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 5)
    - Volume 2, 1896-1898
- Pittsburgh Bureau of Electricity -- Wiring Permits, II.
  Series II contains information regarding Wiring Permits (1895-1913), including information on the date, permit number, owner, contractor, number of buildings, arc lights, first and second wiring, fixtures, motors, number of h.p., building class and location.
  - Volume 1, 1895-1897 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 6)
  - Volume 2, 1898-1901
  - Volume 3, 1902-1904
  - Volume 4, 1904-1907
  - Volume 5, 1908-1909
  - Volume 6, 1910-1911 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 7)
  - Volume 7, 1912-1913
- Allegheny (Pa.) Department of Public Safety - Bureau of Building Inspection, III.
  Series III contains information regarding Building Permits (1894-1908) such as information on the date, owner, builder, building type, total number of buildings, additions and alterations, number of stories, width, depth, value (cost), building class and location.
  - Building Permits, Volume 1, 1894-1899 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 7)
  - Building Permits, Volume 2, 1900-1901
  - Building Permits, Volume 3, 1902-1908